software engineering radio episode 8
interview with Eric Evans
[Music]
welcome everybody to this new episode of
software engineering radio this is our
second interview episode and this time
we talked to Eric Evans eric is the
author of the domain-driven design book
a book that has been very well received
by the object-oriented software
development community the discussion can
be broken down into three parts in the
first part Eric talks about the main
building blocks of domain driven design
the second part discusses something
called strategic design a set of
practices that helps you build
consistent and well-structured systems
finally in the third part we discuss
about ubiquitous language model driven
development and domain-specific
languages we've recorded the interview
using Skype welcome Eric to software
engineering radio before we actually
talk about the main driven design you
might probably want to introduce
yourself a little bit and tell us
something about your background well I
have been doing object-oriented
programming for about 15 years now and
most of that time has been in various
complicated business systems I worked on
Wall Street for a while and in Silicon
Valley I worked in transportation
systems and banking systems and currency
transfer systems and various kinds of
complex business applications using
object-oriented technology and so a good
deal of my specialty has become modeling
complex domains and implementing models
in object-oriented software and that's
what led to my book domain driven design
was an attempt to capture for people the
successful practices that I had seen are
used well that I had used some of which
have been around for a long time some of
which are relatively new and put it
together into a coherent into a coherent
set of practices and with clear names
so that maybe we could have broader
success than we have had in the past so
your book has been received quite quite
well by the community I guess so can you
can you explain in somewhat more detail
what the idea of domain-driven design is
and what it what distinguishes this
approach from kind of normal
object-oriented what everybody else does
a great deal of domain driven design is
comes straight out of a good
old-fashioned object-oriented design
practices but it is not the same thing
for two reasons one because domain
driven design could be applied outside
of object-oriented design it really
doesn't say that you have to make
objects what it says is that you have to
start from an understanding of the
domain and and focus there first and
build knowledge and refine that
knowledge and develop a model that is
your shared understanding of that domain
and build software based on that
understanding and shaped that software
around that understanding and what
object-oriented software does is gives
you the ability to render in software
some concepts that are natural for
thinking about businesses and there are
other paradigms like say a rule-based
programming that could also be done in a
domain driven fashion the my background
is object-oriented programming an object
are also the mainstream of our current
generation of software and so in effect
it is a way of doing object-oriented
programming but there's another way in
which it's different and that is that a
great deal of quite object-oriented
software is designed and conceived from
a technical point of view you can start
out thinking about a technical problem
and you can come out with an elegant
object-oriented solution to that
technical problem
and the reason for the name
domain-driven design is saying this is
not the right place to start for most
applications not all but most that's the
difference I suppose it's more matter of
where the emphasis lies what you think
about when you do your design work
putting putting functionality of your
business first and technology second
functionality and understanding right
beyond just functionality so in your in
your book you distinguish various parts
of the main term and design some are
more related to programming techno
techniques apples are more process
related or design related so there are I
think five or seven core building blocks
you mentioned you mentioned the book
like entities value objects factories
these kinds of things do you think you
can explain why they play such a central
role and what they mean to developers
why they're important sure as you said
there's the the book tends to bring
together the different pieces that you
need to make domain driven design work
and one of the reasons I think that the
technique hasn't taken off as much is
because it is not particularly a way of
programming or a process or a design
methodology it's it's sort of a
philosophy that cuts across all of these
so that's why the book seems a bit of
this and a bit of that in that sense the
building blocks are important because
what I've observed is that people will
come into a design problem and they will
attack it pretty much from scratch
I mean we've we're still just
everything's an object and what I've
seen is that in well-formed models that
whose purpose is software that there are
certain recurring patterns that they're
that the model objects tend to fall into
a relatively small number of types
and that it's very useful to push your
model concepts to one of these for
example the thing that most people love
to talk about it seems to be the
distinction between entities and value
objects this by the way is not my
original contribution this distinction
has been around for quite a while and
been written about in other books yep
and I think that it's gotten more
attention in my book in it and that's
all to the good but to to distinguish
between these two basically one of them
the entity revolves around identity and
continuity and not around the properties
of the thing so in a metaphor if you
think of a living person there's almost
no attribute of that person that exists
throughout the lifespan of that person
and of course the entity that we
associate with that person exists in
fact long after they're dead and their
body is gone so there's no actual
property that this person has but there
is an identity and it ties together
things that we think are important so
the same is true of objects and you may
have let's say in your system and some
of these objects score so onto people so
that's easy to think about now you might
have a customer object and your customer
object may have importance in the sales
related part of your software so you may
track information about sales calls and
and historical sales volumes and so on
things that your sales people need to
interact with this person contact
information all these things are
changing this seems pretty
straightforward in another part of your
software you may be actually handling
the service to this customer you mean
completely different information about
that customer for the purpose of
providing service to them than you did
for trying to sell things to them
historical sales is not relevant the
contact person that you had there is
probably not relevant because it's
probably somebody who in a procurement
role rather than in a operational role
so you have a completely different model
of this customer for purposes of service
and yet it's the same entity but
contrast this to a value object in a
value object if it's well formed you
don't care about identity there's no
meaningful identity at all a good
example of a value object the kind of
canonical example of a value object that
I tend to use is color so if you want to
describe the color of something you say
it's red you say it's green you know
care if the red color that you were
referring to i yesterday is the same
particular red that it is today I mean
you care that it's the same color but
that's a value a property that you can
describe you don't care if it's the same
red object even in terms of how you
would handle the implementation do you
care about history do you do when you
change this object you throw it away and
get another one the more that kind of
thing you can do having immutable
objects that just are what they are and
when they when you no longer want them
you throw them away and get another one
your system will be a lot easier to
manage because you can make statements
about these objects that are firm and
always true statements which you can't
do very easily about an entity not in
the same way entities are a lot harder
to manage and also a lot of the meaning
of a model
from those value objects people tend to
confuse them with data transfer objects
yeah that's because of a naming conflict
that has been resolved quite recently
only right that's true that that did
aggravate the problem but I think that
that naming conflict arose in part
because people already confuse the two
concepts and hopefully this rename will
help to clarify things in people's minds
you could well have a data transfer
object based on an entity so you might
send some data structure from one system
to another that represented some key
information about your customer and
along with the customer ID and in the
other system it would match that
customer ID up to the customer in that
system and it would start to use that
information in the way that that other
system used customer information another
distinction that I made in that building
block section is I about repositories
and factories and services well anyway
you start making these distinctions and
you start to have a model which has
these kind of objects in it that are
recognizable types and someone knows
some properties that they can trust
about this object if I tell you it's a
value object you can assume all kinds of
things you can assume that this object
will not change that it represents some
information about something rather than
the continuity of an identity if I tell
you that this is a repository you know
that it's probably an abstraction layer
that hides database access of some kind
but you don't have to know the details
of that database access to use the
repository okay so after after coming up
with these with these basic building
blocks like entities value objects
services and the facilities that manage
them repositories and factories there
are some some more like architectural
artists
things like the entire corruption layer
or pluggable component frameworks which
then probably serve as an architectural
base of the technical solution right
right so there is a whole what I refer
to as strategic design I tried to
actually avoid the word Architecture in
the book you'll find it isn't used very
much because I found that it it isn't a
very clearly defined word and and mean
so many things to so many people so I
referred to it as strategic design
because these are kind of design
decisions that affect the trajectory of
the whole project and can have a big
impact far beyond the particular area in
which they're used or rather far beyond
a particular area in which a typical say
object or small set of objects reviews
and yes I've found that certain kinds of
strategic design decisions or
architectural decisions can completely
derail an attempt to do domain driven
design so over the years I've been
involved with a lot of projects that
that were very successful and I've been
involved with some projects that were
total failures and I've been involved
with quite a few projects that and it
meddled through and succeeded but we're
not very exciting and I look to see you
know as I was thinking about writing
this book I really reflected on why why
we ended up on those different paths on
some projects you find that you don't
have some of the basic skills people on
all these projects people had any
intention of creating a domain model and
using that to give them the the
advantageous domain models are supposed
to give you the flexibility the
maintainability the ability to create
something complex without getting
overwhelmed so sometimes they didn't
achieve that because they didn't have
the basic skills to kind of create a
good
check model implemented effectively
tightening up the model and implementing
it effectively that's what the building
blocks are all about also that having a
bit of uniformity they're a common
language and a common set of very basic
concepts that help a team work together
so as I say some teams fail for those
reasons some teams fail because they
never found the model that really broke
through and worked and so there's a
section in here called refactorings Ward
deeper inside it's more about how do you
explore and find a really piercing
domain model and how does that
evolutionary process work but some of
them did all these things right and they
still didn't achieve the goal and
sometimes it was because of things that
were beyond the control of an individual
developer or even sometimes our team
sometimes it was an architectural
decision made either at the whole team
level or often for an entire department
that just basically undermined what they
were doing there's quite a variety of
these I tried to focus on three aspects
in the strategic design section and the
most important one is the one you refer
to when you mentioned the
anti-corruption layers that's what I
call context mapping the basic thought
there is it's really more of an
observation that in any sizable project
you will have more than one model and if
you don't consciously manage this the
different models will contaminate each
other and will muddle and and what
you'll end for them is a muddle you
won't have the clarity that a model
needs to be really useful because you'll
have concepts that are mixtures
these different models well run projects
usually do informally distinguish
between the areas of the system that are
applying different models as I mentioned
most of what's in the book has been our
successful practices from the past but
this is one which has been done in a
kind of intuitive way on some projects
but not on all projects by any means and
not consistently and because it's been
done so intuitively there's no
vocabulary at all to describe what's
being done in some ways I think that
that context mapping process in chapter
14 might be the most fundamental
contribution of the book the one that's
the most missing from what most people
do your book also contains a couple of
maybe let's call it tips or best
practices for the design process one
thing I really like is the ubiquitous
language I use it all the time in the
context of meta models you want to
elaborate couple of sentences on these
yeah I would say that in addition to
context mapping ubiquitous language is
the other really fundamental thing what
it means is that rather than one way of
putting it is that rather than focusing
on artifacts that such as say UML
diagram or whatever that reflect the
model that you focus on the language of
the project and your goal in modeling is
really the evolution of a better
language to talk about your domain and
this language is not just used in
conversations among the domain among the
modelers it's used in conversations
between developers conversations between
domain experts and developers
conversations about the system but it's
also used in the code itself so that you
name your object
appropriately and the relationships
between them so that they correspond to
the way you would talk about them in the
tests and everything you've got this
evolving language that runs through
everything which is what ubiquitous
means so it becomes a ubiquitous
language that is anchored in a
conceptual model of the domain it's kind
of related I mean one of the one of the
movements that tries to carry this to
its logical extreme is the
domain-specific languages right which I
find very interesting I would have
mentioned this topic later so okay let's
come back to that one yeah I mean now
you mentioned it so so do you think
there is a relationship between your
approach and domain-specific languages
and all this model driven development
stuff and also what's the what's the
importance of modeling if you talk about
modeling I always think I understand
also from your book that you see
basically well written code as the model
whereas other people think the model is
you know like more like UML diagram what
do you think is the relationship between
those how important is UML based design
in your approach okay
that's a good question let me start by
saying what I what I really think a
model is I think a model is really a set
of related concepts that can be applied
to solve some problem and that's a very
abstract definition of a model but
actually but I think it is in fact the
definition of model and all of these
other things are specific artifacts that
are used to communicate about a model or
to describe or specify it but the model
itself is a set of abstractions a set of
rules of how these abstractions interact
to solve some problem and it's useful to
strip back to that original definition
of model we've gotten so far away from
it I think in the early days when the
term model first started being applied
to the software realm I assume was when
Simula came along I was that's before my
time but I I think that's probably
around the time that this started to be
applied and so because they had created
a language that was specifically
designed to express models over time it
became synonymous and so people from
that kind of background that kind of
historical path sort of view the code as
being the model and that's probably the
closest to my own in the sense that I
was a small talk program our first so I
think of well-written code as being the
most important expression of the model
but I don't think of it as the model
itself and I do think that that fine
distinction is an important one
so other expressions to the model in
fact exist on the project one is UML
diagrams which I find useful especially
if they are not complete the more
complete they are the less useful they
are because what makes them useful is
how they can be used to highlight the
important things and distill the
conceptual parts and separate them from
the more incidental parts and focus
attention on something all of these
things go away when you try to let's say
generate a program based on a UML model
this together a problem where you have
for each class in your code you have a
box on your screen with all the details
exactly then it's easier to look at the
code for me and the two are
indistinguishable in their content to me
a UML diagram that's well crafted gets
rid of the clutter focuses someone's
attention on the key aspects brings out
the abstraction more vividly than it
would be in the code but you can't
generate a program from a UML diagram
like that that you can communicate
important things to another person that
way so so so if we look at the model
the main area then when people tried to
capture the complete semantics of
something with a specifically crafted
modeling language do you think that fits
well with your domain development style
so you asked in fact a few minutes ago
how what was the relationship between
domain driven design and domain-specific
languages or model-driven architecture
or these other approaches what I would
say is the I hesitate to say this
because it sounds so grandiose but I
actually don't mean it that way
I would say that both of those are
attempts at finding better ways of doing
domain driven design so I was really
completely yeah so the fundamental idea
of domain driven design is that we
enable ourselves to focus on the
business and with or that whatever our
domain is and that we aren't focusing
primarily on technical solutions to
technical problems and that's what both
MDA and domain-specific languages are
trying to accomplish so far I haven't
seen much in the MDA realm that has been
useful to me in this way unfortunately
it seems that you know the
transformation layers and so on seem to
add in a great deal of concentration on
the technical the biggest problem there
for me is that you have to express the
model in UML which I find to be an
awkward language for that fine detail
expression of models so perhaps someone
will take some of the things that the
MDA people have worked out and maybe
they'll create a new modeling language
to lay on top of it or who knows what
will happen I mean I I think experiments
are great and I hope that people
continue trying all sorts of things it's
way too soon to standardize on something
if you ask me we haven't done yet we
haven't had a period of wild
experimentation that hit on good good
solutions and I think that tendency is
always more or less already more or less
obvious because
MDA copyright OMG thing which uses UML
for all that stuff is not used by too
many people most people built their own
language is to express specifically what
they need and that's probably more in
your euro spirit yeah yeah that and
which brings us to the domain-specific
languages the domain-specific languages
is something that I find is very
exciting I feel like surely that is part
of the future of domain driven design
but I think there are a couple of blind
alleys that people tend to go down there
one of them for me is this is a big one
that most of the particular techniques
for creating domain-specific languages
create this very sharp line between
those who develop the language and those
who use the language this seems
unnatural to me in the successful
projects that I was in as we would
address domain problems we would modify
our model and and let's say we were
working in small talk the small talk
code would be refined to the point where
we could make statements in small talk
that looked almost like a
domain-specific language and but
furthermore as we would address a new
problem we wouldn't just say okay we'll
use the language that we have to solve
this problem now well we might if it
would fit but very quickly we would drop
streets saying how do we have to change
the language to make it possible to
express this situation we're in very
concisely and clearly if you've got this
very big separation between those who
use the language and those who create
the language you don't have that kind of
closed loop so the language itself
doesn't evolve to handle the domain the
the deeper and deeper in a in a more
powerful way this is the problem that I
see I could see that there are certain
kinds of domain situations where this is
perfectly fine
whether it's naturally separated
to different users I mean take one
example if you're if you're creating
some kind of industrial equipment that's
highly programmable so you create a
domain-specific language that will allow
engineers in a factory let's say to
program the machine to do the things
that they need it to do well in this
case the range of things the machine
does is limited and very well defined
and the range of things that the
engineers and the factory will need it
to do is something that those people are
not going to be able to be involved in
it's it's just the right situation to
have this kind of laying this kind of
approach that splits the two apart but
if we're talking about let's say I don't
know banking software the idea that one
group would create a set of primitives
or relatively high level concepts even
that the other group would then use I
just don't find that it works that well
I think that it starts to break down
because the underlying model hasn't
evolved long enough to really give them
what they need this is actually a really
good point because most of model driven
development today concerns technology so
you automate you know working with j2ee
or you automate working with some other
component platform and in this case it
probably does make sense to have this
group of people who defines the language
because it's limited by the technology
that's the machine metaphor you just
mentioned and the other group who uses
it but if the DSL covers domain concepts
like banking radio astronomy or vehicle
management or these kinds of things then
it's probably absolutely yeah just what
you said that it's important that the
domain experts use the language and
evolve the language to reflect their
deeper understanding yeah they did or if
if not the domain experts themselves
because sometimes domain experts don't
have the kind of rigorous model thinking
that it would take to design this
language but to have this partnership
this close collaborative partnership
between software experts and domain
experts
that's that are constantly evolving the
the model end and the language that
excites used to make expressions in that
model that that I think is if we can get
something that gives us that you know a
domain-specific language technology that
lets us do that then I think we'll
really have something okay so before we
wrap up I would like to ask one one last
question your book contains a lot of
patterns you have written many parts of
it in pattern style on the other hand
it's not you know it's not title domain
driven design patterns or patterns for
the mind of InDesign so why is that I
mean while ago the word pattern in tile
in the title was a good sales argument
right and you decided not to do that yes
why well that was quite a dis conscious
decision on my part I thought and it was
one that maybe the publisher wasn't so
happy about because as you say it was
considered a sales point and maybe it
still is but I felt that patterns you're
right there are lots of patterns in the
book but I felt like it had gotten to
the point where patterns were digested
and now what was interesting wasn't the
fact that you're using patterns it was
what what was the thing that this book
was supposed to show you how to do you
know I could have called it domain
driven design in chapters you know
because the book is broken into chapters
and chapters is a wonderful organizing
principle for a book but very few books
draw attention to that in the title now
this book is about domain driven design
and in fact in my case it was especially
important I thought and here's why
because one of my points one of my basic
drum beats is that we get distracted
from the central issue which is the
domain to understand that domain and
build software that really works within
that domain we get distracted from that
by all kinds of supporting things like
the technologies that we do in fact need
and that are so
very interesting to us but these
techniques are means to an end and that
end is domain well in the same way if I
had called this book domain driven
design patterns I would have been
getting distracted by the technique the
technique being patterns instead of
staying focused on the core the
important goal which was communicating
about domain driven design so that was
why that didn't appear in the title yet
many people say that it's actually a
sign of patterns maturity if it's not
necessary anymore you know to mention it
so they become really what they are our
means of expression of specifying things
in a very particularly useful or
understandable way I completely agree
with that
okay so definitely last question
anything you're working on right now
another book coming out maybe soon so
what can we expect in the future
well what I'm one thing I am working on
right now that I think might be
interesting to people is there's a open
source code library called time and
money one of the things that I found
people asking for was examples working
examples you know and I I thought well I
didn't really learn object-oriented
design from a book so much as I did from
working with well-designed code and so
from many angles I thought we need some
good code libraries out there that are
kind of designed around this philosophy
and some of them and also there are some
some kind of gaps in what we have to use
too so that we spend an inordinate
amount of time doing kind of low-level
things and two of these domains that
seem to be weak in the Java world where
time because of the you know pretty well
known deficiencies of the Java util date
and calendar classes yeah and and money
where there are a lot of subtleties of
working with
that's different than working with
numbers of other kinds so we set out to
to do this to fill this gap a bit and do
it in a completely out there for
everyone to see so that they could be
involved watch it evolve so there's a
SourceForge project called time and
money that's one of the things that I
think people will find interesting and
wait we we get to use it as a bit of a
testbed for ideas such as see how far
you can push this idea of a
domain-specific language that's really
implemented in Java things like that but
at least trying to make this this
codebase supple in the sense that it's
something that developers will enjoy
working with it will feel right to them
it will give them flexibility where they
need flexibility it will be simple and
out of their way where they are not
interested in getting into the details
and but at the same time completely open
so that to whatever extent they want to
they can dive in we put it under the MIT
license so that it's as as free as can
be you know people can change it they
can use it in commercial products
whatever they want it's you know it's
very open okay anything else you want to
mention I can't think of anything right
now the ubiquitous language context
mapping those are the places it starts
and I do appreciate the interview there
was a lot of fun yeah thank you for
being on the show and good luck with
your whatever you do next
[Music]
this was another episode of software
engineering radio the software
engineering radio team wants to thank
Henning poly for providing the music as
well as Lipson comm for hosting in
bandwidth for more information on the
podcast past episodes and feedback go to
s e - radio dotnet
[Music]